<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Censura cleri, or A plea against scandalous ministers, not fit to be restored to the churches livings in point of prudence, piety, and fame. By a true lover of the Church of England in doctrine, ceremony and discipline.</title>
            <author>Barnard, John, d. 1683.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 52 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A78174</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B852</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1035_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R209059</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867964</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867964</idno>
            <idno type="VID">168928</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A78174)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 168928)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 153:E1035[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Censura cleri, or A plea against scandalous ministers, not fit to be restored to the churches livings in point of prudence, piety, and fame. By a true lover of the Church of England in doctrine, ceremony and discipline.</title>
                  <author>Barnard, John, d. 1683.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 21, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Giles Calvert at the Blackspread-Eagle at the West end of Pauls,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A true lover of the Church of England = John Barnard.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July 26".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Clergy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Clergy --  Legal status, laws, etc. --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:168928:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>CENSVRA CLERI,</hi> OR A PLEA Againſt Scandalous MINISTERS, Not fit to be reſtored to the Churches Livings in point of Prudence, Piety, and Fame.</p>
            <p>By a true Lover of the Church of <hi>England</hi> in Doctrine, Ceremony and Diſcipline.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>ROMANS 2.24.</hi>
               </bibl> The Name of God is blaſphemed among the Gentiles through you.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>S. Bern in coen. Dom. Ser. fol. 1683.</hi>
               </bibl> Non enim provenit dignitas in hoc nomine, quod eſt Sacerdos, non (inquam) nomine ſed unitate: converſatione, non officio: merito non vocabulo, Sanctitate non miniſterio.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Giles Calvert</hi> at the Blackſpread-Eagle at the Weſt end of <hi>Pauls.</hi> 1660.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:168928:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:168928:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Cenſura Cleri,</hi> OR A Plea againſt Scandalous Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, not fit to be reſtored to the Churches Livings.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>OR <hi>Sion</hi> ſake I cannot <hi>hold</hi> my peace, who am a true <hi>lover</hi> of the Church of <hi>England</hi> in its doctrine, <hi>ceremony</hi> and diſcipline; I believe the pureſt and <hi>Apoſtolical</hi> of any Chriſtian <hi>Church</hi> in the world; O my <hi>bowels,</hi> my <hi>bowels</hi> are troubled within me! When I ſaw the violent <hi>endeavours</hi> of ſome, who ſhould be more tender of the Churches <hi>welfare,</hi> peace, and honour, that profeſs themſelves <hi>true ſons</hi> of it, yet their <hi>actings</hi> do manifeſt <hi>the contrary,</hi> ſo incongruous to the <hi>princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples</hi> of reaſon, piety, and prudence, that in the <hi>juſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoration</hi> of orthodox, <hi>holy,</hi> and learned men into their ſpiritual <hi>livings</hi> and <hi>promotions,</hi> they would reſtabliſh the wicked debauched Clergy, who are notoriouſly ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous, and have been the overthrow of our moſt glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Church, the reproach of Proteſtant <hi>Religion,</hi> and the juſt <hi>odium</hi> of the people in this Nation; that I won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der as St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> could not be reſtrained from writing his excellent <hi>Notions</hi> of the City of God, <hi>quippe zelo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus Dei exardeſcens,</hi> becauſe he was inflamed with the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:168928:3"/>
               <hi>zeal</hi> of Gods houſe, that I ſee not many <hi>Pens</hi> taken as it were from the wings of a <hi>Seraphim,</hi> and inflamed with a coal from the Altar to declare their <hi>zeal</hi> for the Temple of God againſt drunkards, ſwearers, prohane perſons, who ſhould be ſcourged out as they were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervedly by <hi>Cromwell,</hi> that <hi>flagellum Dei,</hi> the rod of Gods correction upon the Nation, and overthrown as the buyers, and ſellers, and money-changers; nay the gates thereof as of <hi>Paradiſe</hi> ſhould be ſhut up againſt them, that they never offer ſacrifice of polluted lips more, who have cauſed the <hi>offering</hi> of the Lord to be abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the <hi>Sanctuary</hi> like <hi>Elies</hi> ſons. What though they were erected by an extraneous power, which judged in the throne of Gods Church, as well as in the Courts of civil judicature over his Majeſties ſubjects! yet the perſons of ſuch <hi>Clergy</hi> known ſo infamouſly <hi>ſcandalous,</hi> that the Countrey ringed with the common fame of their vices, witneſſes many produced to atteſt the <hi>rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity</hi> of their crimes, that they were not forged calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niations, and ſtill are in readineſs to aſſert the ſame up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on oath, ſhall we in all haſte reſtore them before the <hi>matters</hi> of <hi>charge</hi> be cleared, whereof they ſtill ſtill ſtand accuſed? As I ſaw then their <hi>deprivations</hi> from their <hi>livings</hi> was not much judged, their very Friends being aſhamed to <hi>ſolicite</hi> their cauſe before an Uſurped pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; ſo their preſent <hi>reſtitution</hi> in the countrey to their <hi>places</hi> is ſo far from being deſired, that the very <hi>name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> of their return is ſo <hi>odious</hi> to the people, that it cannot be heard with any <hi>patience.</hi> I ſpeak of ſuch Clergy as have been <hi>deprived</hi> purely upon the <hi>account</hi> of ſcandall by the pretended <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Cromwell,</hi> as for common <hi>drinking, ſwearing</hi> and <hi>carding</hi> and dicing in an <hi>Ale-houſe,</hi> or in other publike <hi>houſes;</hi> and not of thoſe who were wickedly thruſt out of their livings for the conſtant <hi>tenure</hi> of a good <hi>Conſcience,</hi> adhering to their principle of <hi>Loyalty</hi> to the King, and obedience to the eſtabliſhed <hi>orders</hi> of the Church; ſo that if there ſhall be a promiſcuous <hi>reduction</hi> of them all into their Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:168928:3"/>without any ſpecial note of <hi>diſcrimination</hi> upon them, who are <hi>worthy;</hi> and who are not; who ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for the <hi>Miniſtry,</hi> and who are not; but all ruſh in a croud to the Churches <hi>Patrimony,</hi> and celebrate her ſacred offices, wicked and ungodly with their unſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied lips, and hands to offer up ſacrifices for the people, as if the <hi>flood gates</hi> were let open to <hi>irreligion</hi> and <hi>prophaneſs</hi> upon this change, for debauched livers to ſwim in the <hi>Sea</hi> of their former luſt and <hi>pleaſure,</hi> and not the way open to piety, ſtrictneſs and order amongſt all ranks of men, and <hi>Miniſters</hi> eſpecially; if this be the fruits of Gods mercies and <hi>deliverances</hi> to us, which have been wonderfull to the acknowledgement of our <hi>enemies,</hi> we muſt not expect a <hi>bleſſing</hi> from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven upon the Nation, nor the long continuance of our <hi>Church</hi> in its excellent conſtitution: but as <hi>Hooker</hi> obſerved, it had but the <hi>Age of a man</hi> in its beſt eſtate, when it flouriſhed with the outward riches of honour and glory, to the envy and admiration of other Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, we may fear it will live <hi>but the day of an infant,</hi> that is unnaturally born, when it ſhall <hi>cheriſh</hi> and <hi>nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh</hi> ſuch monſters and <hi>Vipers</hi> in its breſt as ſcandalous Miniſters to feed upon her <hi>milk,</hi> who will afterwards with more cruelty then <hi>Nero,</hi> not only deteſt but eat out the very <hi>bowels</hi> of this their tender Mother.</p>
            <p>The reaſons which ſhould induce then all honeſt <hi>Sons</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> for the preſent <hi>ſtop,</hi> and admiſſion of ſuch injuſtice, eſpecially they which are in <hi>Authority,</hi> and have their daily emanation from the Head of our <hi>gracious Soveraign</hi> to cheriſh and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liven their juſt actions and Counſels, for the <hi>happy eſtabliſhment</hi> of our Church and Kingdom: let them impartially weigh the merit of the cauſe, in the <hi>ballance</hi> of reaſon, juſtice, and conſcience, and then it will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear I hope to their full <hi>ſatisfaction,</hi> for piety ſake, prudence, fame, and our Churches honour, they ſhould not be reſtored, but at preſent ſuſpended, untill a <hi>reex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination</hi> of their caſe before a lawfull <hi>Authority</hi> is
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:168928:4"/>made to have the <hi>depoſitions</hi> of the ſame witneſſes upon their oaths, who are ready to appear; and who ſhould ſeem againſt this Chriſtian <hi>propoſall</hi> which ſavours ſo much of equity I know not; but all men are rather bound to have wickedneſs brought to <hi>light,</hi> and that which is the <hi>work</hi> of the <hi>devil</hi> to ſhame and confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, conſidering the nature of offence in a Miniſter who is a <hi>publike</hi> perſon doth draw a reproach upon religion and the heavenly <hi>calling</hi> he hath taken upon him: that his ejection from the Church, when he hath miniſtred a juſt ſcandall to the people inſtead of a good exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, is but a <hi>puniſhment</hi> commenſurate with his <hi>crime,</hi> that deſerves no leſs then deprivation, if not a to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall excluſion <hi>ab officio &amp; beneficio</hi> while he lives, of which we ſhall ſpeak more fully afterwards.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe ſuch have violated and broken their ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred <hi>vow</hi> and <hi>promiſe</hi> at their ordination, when they were made <hi>Deacons</hi> and <hi>Prieſts</hi> by the Biſhop; and this doth ſo evidently appear by the ſolemn <hi>charge</hi> that the Biſhop doth impoſe upon their calling into theſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees and offices in the Church, that any one who reads the <hi>book</hi> of Ordination may ſee how juſtly they have <hi>merited</hi> their ejection out of the Church by having leſs conſcience then <hi>Infidels,</hi> among whom the bonds of covenant and vows are ſacred; yet theſe violate their oath, break their <hi>faith,</hi> evacuate their promiſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traying that ſingular <hi>truſt</hi> and charge which the Biſhop doth repoſe in them when he conſecrates their <hi>perſons</hi> to ſo high a calling, as Deacon and Prieſt, which is done with that admirable <hi>ſolemnity,</hi> to inforce the deeper impreſſion of reverence and obedience to Ordination, that which muſt needs prefer it above all other Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical <hi>Ordinances.</hi> Now let us hear what the Biſhop giveth in to his <hi>Candidate</hi> when he ordains a Deacon or a Prieſt: Firſt he ſolemnly put them in mind of their duty, the greatneſs of their office, the danger and fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full conſequence that follows the neglect.<note place="margin">Book of Ord. <hi>p. 2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Have alwayes printed in your remembrance, ſaith he, how great a trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:168928:4"/>is committed to your charge; [What treaſure is this? that is, the ſouls of the people, which are of more inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luable price, then the treaſures of many worlds,] for they be the ſheepe of Chriſt, which be bought with his death, and for whom he ſhed his blood; the Church and congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation whom you muſt ſerve, is his Spouſe and body; if it chance the ſame Church, or member thereof, take any hurt or hinderance by reaſon of your negligence, you know the greatneſs of the fault, and alſo that horrible puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment doth enſue.</hi> Can there any thing more <hi>divinely</hi> be uttered for the demonſtration of a Miniſters duty, and the ſetting forth his charge with <hi>terror,</hi> in caſe he ſhould <hi>break</hi> the ſame, which no doubt is a ſin <hi>of that nature</hi> of provocation, as not only draws him before the Eccleſiaſtical ſeat of <hi>Judicature,</hi> whereby he will be <hi>judged</hi> worthy of deprivation, but alſo before the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſeat of God, whereby he will be arraigned unto condemnation! For if the breach of <hi>vows</hi> and <hi>promiſes</hi> is a ſin contrary to the light and practice of the <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles,</hi> who were faithfull performers of what they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed before their <hi>Gods</hi> and their <hi>Prieſts;</hi> much more doth a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> and a Miniſter offend the Almighty, before whom, and his Biſhops, and Presbyters he doth make a ſolemn vow at Ordination, and then <hi>breaks</hi> it. Let us hear further what he engages to. Will you give your faithfull diligence, ſaith the Biſhop, alwayes ſo to miniſter the doctrine, and Sacraments, and diſcipline of Chriſt, as the Lord hath commanded, and as the Realm hath received the ſame according to the commandment of God? I will, ſaith he, by the help of God. What ſhall we ſay of him that went out of the Church to <hi>ſpue</hi> before the conſecration of the <hi>Sacrament,</hi> becauſe he had overcharged his <hi>ſtomack</hi> with drink; hath not he broken his vow of ordination, and is worthy of <hi>ejection?</hi> Will you be diligent to frame and faſhon your own <hi>ſelves</hi> and your <hi>families</hi> according to the <hi>doctrine</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and to make both your <hi>ſelves</hi> and your families as much as in you <hi>lyeth,</hi> wholeſome examples and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:168928:5"/>ſpectacles to the flock of Chriſt Jeſus? I will ſaith the Prieſt apply my ſelf, the Lord being my <hi>help.</hi> Certainly thou prophane man, ſhalt be judged out of thy own mouth, who haſt been an <hi>example</hi> of wickedneſs, a leader of the people to the gates of Hell and deſtruction, who haſt <hi>the keyes put</hi> into thy hands by ordination, to open the <hi>doors of Heaven.</hi> If this be ſuffered, what conſcience will the <hi>people</hi> have of their vows &amp; promiſes, when they ſee the Prieſt or Deacon go away <hi>unpuniſhed,</hi> whoſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity of life being a <hi>condition</hi> whereby he is received into holy orders, the wilfull breach thereof deſerves no leſs upon <hi>proof</hi> then the degrading him from the work of the Miniſtry, and forfeiting his <hi>living</hi> by <hi>ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dall;</hi> when he that breaks his truſt in any <hi>civil office,</hi> that he holds in the Kingdom, is adjudged worthy of being <hi>diſplaced;</hi> much more who beareth rule in the Church of God ought upon <hi>misbehaviour</hi> forthwith to be expelled.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Theſe ſcandalous Miniſters have corrupted our Gentry and moſt ingenuous ſpirits in the Nation with <hi>ſpeculative</hi> and <hi>practical</hi> Atheiſm, that religion is eſteemed a <hi>mockery,</hi> and a ſubtill artifice of deceit to <hi>poſſeſs</hi> the people with Chimeraes, fancies, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages of timerous men according to <hi>Lucretius, Primus in orbe deos fecit timor,</hi> that we are debarred from the ſweet enjoyment of that lawfull liberty which otherwiſe we might uſe. Are not their thoats a common <hi>ſepulcher</hi> to iſſue out ſuch unſavory ſpeeches? what is their ordinary diſcourſe but <hi>Rablais</hi> language to confirm one another in liberty and Atheiſm? and when <hi>Gentlemen</hi> ſee a Miniſters vitious life ſo diametri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally <hi>oppoſite</hi> to his doctrine, though he preaches the judgement of <hi>hell,</hi> Gods wrath, and eternal <hi>damnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> yet not ſcrupling to commit the ſame ſins againſt which he <hi>thunders</hi> forth judgement: what can they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve but that he is a religious <hi>Mountebanck,</hi> and juggler, and ſpeaks out of the Pulpit as from his ſtage to get money of the people, and he only preacheth <hi>ex officio</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:168928:5"/>to receive his tithes and profits, is not this the common exprobration of Gentry againſt Miniſters, and grown proverbiall in the mouthes of the people, that let them ſharpen their doctrine and reproof with never ſo keen an edge of their ſpirituall ſword, yet they can dull its encounter from any powerfull execution with this ready anſwer, <hi>O Doctor, intus reſpice labium tuum; fac quod dicis, operare quod praedicas;</hi> and in the words of the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.21. <hi>Thou</hi> which <hi>teacheſt another,</hi> teacheſt thou <hi>not thy ſelf?</hi> thou which preacheſt a man <hi>ſhould not ſteal,</hi> doſt thou <hi>ſteal?</hi> That ſayſt a <hi>man ſhall</hi> not commit adultery, <hi>doſt thou commit adultery?</hi> that makeſt thy boaſt of the law, doſt thou diſhonour God, that his name is blaſphemed among the <hi>Gentiles</hi> through you? Let us mark our ingenious-ſpirits in the countrie, how they are chiefly led aſide and <hi>corrupted,</hi> where they have a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauched <hi>Miniſtry</hi> in their pariſh, by whom they <hi>juſtifie</hi> their miſpending of precious time, and palliate the crimes of <hi>drinking,</hi> idle talking and common ſwearing, with the <hi>Apology</hi> of their example; and this prodigality of time, with their eſtates, <hi>dribling</hi> away in cups to the deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of their families and diſhonour of their perſons, they <hi>chriſten</hi> in their drink, with the excellent <hi>name</hi> of Society, good fellowſhip, and liberall <hi>fruition</hi> of each other; as if there was not a more generous way of enjoyment, both for free communication, and diverſion of <hi>pleaſure</hi> and delight, then in a paltry <hi>Ale-houſe,</hi> the common receptacle of infamous and vile per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, who have no other <hi>Sanctuary</hi> for their revel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, to form a diſcourſe ſutable to the liberty and <hi>extravagancy</hi> of the place; is not the <hi>Theme</hi> common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly betwixt him and the Miniſter (who muſt conform himſelf to his <hi>Patrons</hi> humor) either obſcene, <hi>idle,</hi> and misbecoming both, or elſe Atheiſticall, profane, <hi>Celſian</hi> and <hi>Julian</hi> like, ſcoffing at the auſterity and rigid beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour of Chriſtians; that Religion is but a State <hi>trick</hi> of wiſe invention, the device of Kings and Governours, a <hi>Political</hi> Engine to draw people into blind obedience
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:168928:6"/>and ſubjection to their powers; and keep this wilde beaſt of <hi>many heads,</hi> the common people, <hi>awed</hi> with a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion of conſcience, they muſt not thruſt forth the horns of <hi>rebellion</hi> againſt any civil power? what ſhall we ſay of their pains taken betwixt the <hi>cup</hi> and the <hi>lip,</hi> to ſet forth the variety of Religions <hi>as Varro</hi> did amongſt the Heathens, to deſtroy the <hi>belief</hi> of all; that the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplicity of <hi>opinions,</hi> differing as wide as the <hi>poles,</hi> is like the contention among the Philoſophers, dogmatizing ſeverall wayes, according to the <hi>Number</hi> of their <hi>Sects;</hi> and none of them holding the truth, but all their prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples may be diſproved? Nay when Religion is granted for a truth in the confeſſion of our more learned gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, do not they add to it the looſe ſuperſtructures of <hi>Hobbs, Osborn,</hi> and others of the <hi>Atheiſticall</hi> tribe, which they build upon the foundation on purpoſe to overthrow it, and with it the precepts of <hi>faith,</hi> life, and good <hi>manners?</hi> are not theſe the Authors, and ſuch like, wherein they are verſed through their diligent <hi>reading</hi> them above all other books, as if they were their Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſme? Now for the Miniſter and <hi>ghoſtly</hi> father to joyn iſſue with ſuch <hi>profane</hi> and ungodly men, as it were in the Dialogues of <hi>Bernardinus Ochinus,</hi> to make all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious <hi>impoſtures,</hi> to queſtion our received <hi>principles</hi> of Scripture, Fathers, Councils in former ages, and manage a diſcourſe of <hi>Libertiniſme</hi> &amp; Atheiſm pleaſing to his Patrons ears, to talk <hi>ſlieghtly</hi> and merrily of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, as the Prieſts and <hi>Friers</hi> did of old, &amp; that Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal did of <hi>Melanchton,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mel. Adam in vita Mel.</note> who thought he was a wiſer man then to believe the <hi>reſurrection</hi> of the body; add to theſe (which I am ſure have been the ſubject of ſome diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes) the intolerable ſcandal they have given in their lives by <hi>roaring,</hi> ſwearing and <hi>drinking:</hi> I think the purging them out of the <hi>Church,</hi> by whatſoever <hi>power</hi> erected, as the putting away of <hi>Locuſts</hi> and <hi>Caterpillers</hi> from the deſtroying the fruit of the <hi>trees</hi> in a curious <hi>garden,</hi> ſhould be accounted a good <hi>act</hi> done by any hand: their detruſion out of the Church good men
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:168928:6"/>have not pitied, but <hi>bewailed</hi> the rather, that the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſneſs of government in former time occaſioned that to be done by an <hi>invading</hi> hand, which ſhould have been performed <hi>regularly.</hi> Is not the ſaying of <hi>Horace</hi> true, <hi>Decipit exemplar vitiis imitabile.</hi> Surely,<note place="margin">Hor. ep. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> of all ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples the Miniſter is moſt imitable, both in the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try and Commonalty of the Nation, who bear ſo aw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full a reverence to their Learning and Calling, that what they ſay or do, is taken for an <hi>Oracle</hi> and Rule, being ſuppoſed to be wiſer and more knowing then all other, as the <hi>Druides</hi> were among the old <hi>Brittains,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gild.</note> if they are not holier; that if the ſalt of theſe <hi>grave</hi> lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned perſons have loſt its ſavour of <hi>morality,</hi> piety, and mortification, what is it good for but to be caſt into the <hi>dunghill?</hi> If their communication which ſhould mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter grace to the <hi>Hearers,</hi> tends either to Libertiniſm, Obſceneſs, Prophaneſs, or Atheiſm, and the whole <hi>courſe</hi> of their life is ungodly and wicked through ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous ſins, what reaſon or piety is there to be alledged they ſhould continue in ſo holy a calling, or that they ſhould wear the habit of <hi>Sacred orders,</hi> to the reproach of their own <hi>function,</hi> but forthwith be degraded, or at leaſt ſuſpended from the exerciſe of their miniſterial office; much leſs have thoſe <hi>Souls</hi> depoſited again into their <hi>hands,</hi> who have led them the way to <hi>hell</hi> by Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of their example. When alſo they have ſinned both againſt the <hi>Law</hi> of God, the Civil Law, and the <hi>Canonical</hi> Laws of the Church, which enjoyn, a rigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity of ſtrictneſs in their lives, above all other;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tit.</hi> 17. <hi>Na.</hi> 134.</note> 
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>na eſt eorum converſatio &amp; orantium &amp; quae naturae ſunt opera facientium, quatenus inculpabiles &amp; inaccuſabiles conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant.</hi> Their converſation ſhould be altogether ſuch as thoſe that are given to prayer, and doing works of that <hi>nature,</hi> as that they may ſtand <hi>unblamable</hi> and unaccu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; and by the ancient Apoſtolicall <hi>Canons</hi> we find them worthy to be <hi>deprived ipſo facto</hi> for neglecting the <hi>cure</hi> of ſouls upon misbehaviour; <hi>Epiſcopus, vel Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byter, cleri vel populi curam non gerens, deponatur:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Can. Ap. <hi>58.</hi>
               </note> The
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:168928:7"/>Biſhop or Prieſt neglecting his care of the Clergy and people, ſhall forthwith be <hi>depoſed</hi> of their Office.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It is to be <hi>lamented</hi> how they have brought both the <hi>calling</hi> and the perſons of their fellow brethren in the <hi>Miniſtry</hi> into contempt and diſgrace by the <hi>Gentry</hi> and people, among whom they have been eſteemed the filth and <hi>offscouring</hi> of all things, into which they have poured forth their <hi>obloquy</hi> and dirty ſpeeches, in the ſcandall of thoſe men; or elſe why ſhould not an <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> Clergy-man be honoured as much as a <hi>Scotch</hi> Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byter, in the Country of <hi>Scotland,</hi> or a reformed Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter in the Churches beyond the <hi>Sea,</hi> who have not nigh ſuch eſtates of <hi>preferment</hi> as the Engliſh Clergy, yet have all due reſpect from the people? but thoſe mens <hi>ſins</hi> tolerated, draws an odium upon all the reſt; which are puniſhed immediately without compaſſion in the <hi>Diſcipline</hi> of their Countries: that <hi>Luther</hi> knowing how inſufferable they were in the Church, and might en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danger the reputation and <hi>credit</hi> of the Miniſtry, is ſo far a ſtranger to that fooliſh pity, which ſome teſtifie in their favour, that he would have them impriſoned, and depoſed.<note place="margin">Luth. col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loq. p. <hi>295.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Preachers,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>that are ſcandalous ought to be impriſoned, and put from their office; I have obtained of the prince Elector that a priſon ſhould be built for their diſcipline and puniſhment:</hi> I am ſure it is the Apoſtles rule, that nothing ſhould be <hi>done</hi> whereby the Miniſtry might be <hi>blamed;</hi> And hath not the impudence of <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natiques</hi> taken their riſe for want of this Diſcipline? Had Miniſters been ſo fanned throughly by a <hi>Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of their abuſes, that the Clergy were known to be the moſt holy peculiar <hi>tribe</hi> of the Nation, they would never ſo <hi>pertinaciouſly</hi> have denyed their outward call of <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination,</hi> &amp; from thence conclude themſelves to be more truly Prieſts by their <hi>inward call</hi> of the Spirit, whoſe impulſe they feel <hi>beating them</hi> on to the exerciſe of their pretended <hi>gifts;</hi> whereas they find no fruits of the Spirit in a number of Clergy men, not ſo much as a ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly life of Chriſtianity, not coming up to the <hi>morality</hi> of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:168928:7"/>Heathens; whoſe very <hi>Books</hi> of learning, if they read no other, ſhould <hi>teach</hi> them better. I know not what will wipe away this reproach; but their confeſſion of ſhame, with a <hi>pudet haec opprobria nobis,</hi> and a ſpeedy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation by the Biſhops &amp; Prelates, who, having lain ſo long in a <hi>dead ſleep,</hi> being ſlain in the <hi>exerciſe</hi> of their power, ſhould upon their reſurrection (having a <hi>ſpirit of life</hi> put into them by the vigorous breathings of a gracious <hi>Prince</hi>) judge and condemn thoſe notoriouſly ſcandalous or inſufficient, and ſet free the <hi>innocent</hi> and guiltleſs; a judging and reexamining there ſhould be of every mans <hi>caſe,</hi> or elſe the ſin of not judging ſuch wicked offenders, will ſtill be a <hi>provocation</hi> of God againſt the Nation, and intolerable ſhame and ignomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny fall upon the <hi>Church</hi> and precious <hi>Clergy.</hi> The Church hath never ſpared, but inflicted <hi>puniſhment</hi> on leſſer crimes whenſoever they are proved, not only for incontinency, ſwearing, drinking, but leſs <hi>offences</hi> have no countenance from the Church, but are abſolutely <hi>condemned.</hi> So exemplary a ſtrictneſs would it impoſe upon the Clergy to be patterns of <hi>imitation</hi> to all others; <hi>Deponatur clericus qui in caupona cibum ſumpſerit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Carantza Can. Ap. <hi>54.</hi>
               </note> Let a Clergy man be depoſed for <hi>eating</hi> in a common victual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling-<hi>houſe, viz.</hi> as the <hi>Comment</hi> inſtances it, unleſs it be upon an extraordinary <hi>caſe</hi> of a journey.<note place="margin">Laodic. Conc. Can. <hi>24.</hi>
               </note> The <hi>Laodicean</hi> Council, ſaith, <hi>Nullus Eccleſiaſticorum in tabernis come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere debeat:</hi> No Clergy man ſhould eat in Taverns; why ſo, but becauſe they are <hi>ſcandalous</hi> places for them to frequent, drawing the ſame <hi>Infamy</hi> as if they went into Stews and <hi>Brothell</hi> houſes, becauſe they are places of bad report? doth it not indeed repreſent a ſhamefull <hi>aſpect</hi> of diſgrace upon the whole <hi>cloth,</hi> to behold a Miniſter <hi>cupping</hi> and <hi>piping</hi> with the vulgar people, or the gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try of a diſſolute <hi>life?</hi> what is it but to draw the ſame <hi>reproach</hi> upon Chriſtianity,<note place="margin">Tertull. Apol. cap. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> as <hi>Tertullian</hi> writes of the Heathens, <hi>who carried the images of their gods into Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſes, that Religion may beg an alms there.</hi> Who doth ſo lively repreſent the image of God, in his calling,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:168928:8"/>office, ſanctity, and <hi>purity,</hi> as a Miniſter, who ſpeaks <hi>in perſona Chriſti,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 5.20.</note> that men would be reconciled from their ſin, to the fear of God? and ſhall this be a drunken, ſwearing <hi>image,</hi> wanton and <hi>unclean,</hi> as if the god whom it <hi>Symbolizeth</hi> with, were <hi>Bacchus,</hi> or <hi>Priapus,</hi> or <hi>Florus?</hi> Oh let us purge out all ſcandalous gods. For amongſt the idolatrous prieſts of <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> who were <hi>ſcraped</hi> into the office of Prieſthood, <hi>ex faece populi,</hi> from the dregs of the moſt inferior <hi>people</hi> (ſo men more prone to groſs vices) yet we find them not Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kards, <hi>Whoremaſters,</hi> and common <hi>Swearers;</hi> for then few would have been induced by their example to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip the <hi>Calves</hi> of <hi>Dan</hi> and <hi>Bethel;</hi> much leſs in the number of Chriſts <hi>Apoſtles</hi> do we find any other but one Son of <hi>Perdition,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jerom. in Mat. <hi>26.</hi>
               </note> who was, as S. <hi>Jerom</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalum Chriſti, &amp; omnium Apoſtolorum,</hi> the ſcandal of Chriſt and all his Apoſtles; but it had been better for him never to have been born, then to have brought that <hi>Scandal</hi> into the world. Such an exact behavior there was among the primitive <hi>Chriſtians</hi> in their times, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpotted from vice,<note place="margin">Tertuli. apol. cap. <hi>44.</hi>
               </note> that <hi>Tertulliam</hi> appeals to the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſters of the Heathens for the <hi>unreproachable</hi> teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of their integrity; of all the malefactors brought before you, is there any of them accuſed of <hi>murder, robbery,</hi> or <hi>ſacriledge?</hi> or can you tax them of ſmaller <hi>crimes,</hi> that their life is like other <hi>priſoners,</hi> that is, in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temperance, rudeneſs, <hi>unchaſtity,</hi> gluttony? No ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly we find not the common ſort of Chriſtians <hi>blemiſhing</hi> their profeſſions with <hi>odious</hi> ſins, much leſs their Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops or Prieſts: which the Heathens would have taken notice of ſo <hi>highly,</hi> that what was accounted a <hi>mote</hi> of offence in the leaſt diſordered converſation of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, was a <hi>beam</hi> of great magnitude in a <hi>Miniſter,</hi> and by the Churches cenſure would undoubtedly be ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended, if not utterly deprived of his <hi>office.</hi> And this was indeed the very opinion and practice of the <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles</hi> from the very <hi>light</hi> of nature and <hi>reaſon,</hi> who thought their Prieſts no longer worthy to celebrate <hi>my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:168928:8"/>and holy things, or to continue in the office of <hi>prieſthood,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Roſin. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiq.</note> then they approved themſelves to be of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blamable life; that if the <hi>Veſtall</hi> Virgin ſuffers her <hi>cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtity</hi> to be defloured, ſhe is not only diſcharged of her <hi>office</hi> from ſerving at the ſacred <hi>fires,</hi> but for her Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dall put to a cruell <hi>Death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. It muſt be acknowledged, that ſcandalous Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters have turned the hearts of the people from <hi>Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacy,</hi> and the eſtabliſhed orders of the <hi>Church,</hi> who otherwiſe would have <hi>entirely</hi> loved them, but through <hi>offence</hi> of their ſcandall who were Epiſcopal, did preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice their judgements with a <hi>diſlike</hi> of whatſoever they commended; that they would rather embrace any other form of Church government, <hi>Presbyterian</hi> or <hi>Independent,</hi> then this, which is ſo ancient and proper and deducible from the <hi>Apoſtolicall</hi> times; becauſe the people are more led by the Authority of example then reaſon, both in <hi>Religious</hi> and <hi>Civil</hi> matters, following the preſident of <hi>pious</hi> upright men, and thoſe eſpecially that bear the outward <hi>ſhew of holineſs</hi> above others; as how were they bewitched with the ſeeming ſanctity of the <hi>Scribes</hi> and Phariſees, their painted <hi>Sepulchers</hi> and waſhed <hi>Pots,</hi> their hypocriticall <hi>zeal</hi> of prayer in the ſtreets: A <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retick</hi> of a ſevere life, ſhall <hi>Arius</hi>-like, from one <hi>spark</hi> ſet the whole world on <hi>fire;</hi> That it concerns the <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox</hi> to ſhine in eminency of piety as well as they, and to exceed them in <hi>luſtre</hi> and brightneſs, as the Sun doth the <hi>Stars,</hi> and the Stars the poor <hi>Glowworms.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 King. 2.26.</note> 
               <hi>Abia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thar</hi> muſt be put out, and <hi>Zadock</hi> take his office, becauſe iniquity was found in him, and the other was righteous according to his Name, the Lord ſignifying by <hi>Zadock</hi> what a righteous Miniſtry he will eſtabliſh, and no other in his Church; ſo were all the Apoſtles, and ſeventy diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples except <hi>Judas</hi> the Traitor; and is not this righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs ſutable to their calling and <hi>imployment</hi> they at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, who are to offer up prayers and ſupplications for the Church? that as it is well obſerved by S. <hi>Cyprian,</hi> he that is imployed to prefer the <hi>Petitions</hi> of many to a
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:168928:9"/>
               <hi>King,</hi> muſt be one ſpecially choſen that is a <hi>Favourite</hi> of the <hi>Prince,</hi> or elſe the Petitioners may go without <hi>audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> and relief: So for the offering the Congregations <hi>Petitions</hi> and ſolemn requeſts to the <hi>King</hi> of heaven and earth, its neceſſary he ſhould be <hi>choſen</hi> one who is in grace and <hi>favour</hi> with God for his righteouſneſs of life, and not a drunkard or debauched perſon, to whom God may ſay, What haſt thou to <hi>do</hi> to take my <hi>Name</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thy mouth? And indeed as ſuch Prieſts were former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>debarred</hi> of their ſervice, who had fallen into groſs ſins, and put into <hi>inferiour offices,</hi> becauſe they had gone aſtray; there is the ſame reaſon of excepting againſt a ſcandalous mans <hi>Miniſtry,</hi> that he ſhall not be permitted in the celebration of <hi>high myſteries,</hi> as prayer and interceſſion, and the adminiſtration of the <hi>Sacraments,</hi> but put into ſome inferior <hi>ſervice,</hi> as the Church ſhall think fit, if it ſhould bring back the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent orders of <hi>Lectores, acolouthi,</hi> &amp;c. Rather then they ſhould attend theſe other <hi>grand</hi> adminiſtrations: for God ſaith directly of thoſe <hi>Prieſts</hi> that had gone aſtray from their office, Ezek. 44.13. <hi>They ſhall not come near unto me to do the office of a prieſt, nor come near to any of my holy things in the moſt holy place; what then were they to do?</hi> The inferior parts of the <hi>ſervice,</hi> to keep the charge of the <hi>door,</hi> kill and flay the skin, and prepare the <hi>beaſt</hi> for <hi>ſacrifice,</hi> for which they ſhould have a <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petency</hi> of allowance, as the Sons of <hi>Eli,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.36. Such a piece of ſilver and a <hi>morſell</hi> of <hi>Bread,</hi> that may ſupply their condition from extream <hi>poverty.</hi> What elſe but this can be gathered from the Apoſtles words?<note place="margin">1 Tim. 5.17.</note> the Elder that rules well is worthy of <hi>double</hi> honour, that is, an honourable <hi>maintenance</hi> for his work, and a due reverence to his <hi>Perſon</hi> and calling: Are all deſerving this? No, only he that <hi>rules well,</hi> without blame, giving no <hi>offence,</hi> and taking heed to the flock that is <hi>committed</hi> to him; if he rule <hi>ill,</hi> let him have but the ſingle honour of neceſſary maintenance, becauſe he is worthy of the greateſt <hi>ſhame</hi> that vilifies the order of Evangelical
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:168928:9"/>
               <hi>Prieſt-hood</hi> with the diſgrace of his example, that as St. <hi>Jerom</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>virtus ubique honoretur, vitium deturpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur;</hi> vertue muſt be honoured everywhere,<note place="margin">Jerom. in Jac. c. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> but vice diſgraced, eſpecially in a <hi>Miniſter,</hi> who ſhould be like St. <hi>John</hi> Baptiſt, a burning and a <hi>ſhining</hi> light to others, yet is a <hi>pillar</hi> of <hi>cloud</hi> and darkneſs to obſcure the way to <hi>heaven,</hi> when he alienates the <hi>affections</hi> of people from the <hi>love</hi> of the Church, its <hi>peace,</hi> unity, order from <hi>obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience</hi> to its conſtitutions; when he is a Son of <hi>diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> himſelf by his life, he is neither <hi>worthy</hi> of honour nor continuance in his <hi>place,</hi> but in an inferiour <hi>rank</hi> and <hi>order.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. In point of prudence and <hi>fame,</hi> as the preſent <hi>jun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures</hi> of affairs ſtand, they ought not to be <hi>re-admitted</hi> who are ſo notoriouſly wicked, knowing how many enemies of potent <hi>factions</hi> this poor Church and <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> hath, who watch for all <hi>advantages</hi> to excite the people into <hi>rebellion</hi> and diſobedience againſt his <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty,</hi> and deſire no better <hi>pretences</hi> to ſhake the <hi>foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations</hi> of our peace and ſafety, and to unſettle the <hi>frame</hi> of our civil and Eccleſiaſticall <hi>government,</hi> then the old exclamations, that ſcandalous and corrupt <hi>practices</hi> are tolerated in the <hi>Church,</hi> profaneſs is countenanced when not <hi>puniſhed,</hi> good men diſcouraged when bad men are <hi>preferred,</hi> formality only and <hi>ſhew</hi> of religion is ſet up, but the <hi>power</hi> of godlineſs is <hi>extinguiſhed;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hor. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>urgeris turba circum te ſtante;</hi> we cannot ſtep aſide but the clamour of common <hi>people</hi> thus ſounds in our <hi>ears,</hi> as if moſt conſcientious and ſtrict men would be laid <hi>aſide,</hi> and many regular and orthodox who are placed by Patrons, ſhall now be <hi>diſplaced</hi> by deboiſt and <hi>igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant</hi> perſons; what comfort will <hi>redound</hi> to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, what honour to the Church, what glory to <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty</hi> God in their return, who have been the <hi>inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> of ſhame and confuſion to the Churches <hi>former</hi> happy eſtate, and no doubt but will bring a <hi>ſecond</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation upon it, if we are not <hi>carefull</hi> how to eſtab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh things <hi>piouſly</hi> and prudentially? and ſhall not the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:168928:10"/>wing of fame, (upon whatſoever <hi>extreme</hi> we run into, as we are apt through the <hi>liberty</hi> God hath put into our <hi>hands</hi>) carry our errors <hi>aloft</hi> with multiplied <hi>aggrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> unto the Proteſtant <hi>Churches</hi> abroad, ſome of which being <hi>haters</hi> of our well eſtabliſhed government, would be glad of any <hi>evil</hi> reports that fly abroad to the <hi>diſhonour</hi> of our Iſland, the traducing of <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> and confirming the <hi>opinion</hi> of the more moderate ſort of <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> that ſince there is no <hi>plat-form</hi> of go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment <hi>directly</hi> laid down in the word of God, Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters they ſay, is the <hi>beſt eſtabliſhed</hi> government in the Church they are ſure, if not for the <hi>remedy</hi> of ſchiſm, yet for the <hi>puniſhment</hi> of ſinners and <hi>ſcandalous</hi> offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors. Let no man through favour or affection <hi>therefore</hi> extenuate a <hi>Clergy</hi> mans offences when they are <hi>groſs</hi> and odious, or ſave them from the ſuffering the juſt reward of their ſin, who as they have merited no leſs at the <hi>hands</hi> of God, whoſe judgements are right, ſo no leſs at the <hi>hands</hi> of Tyrants, which are Gods inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to <hi>puniſh</hi> ſin, where the lawfull power is debar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red both in <hi>Church</hi> and State; And would to God ſince our <hi>eyes</hi> are bleſſed in the ſight of a hopefull <hi>flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing</hi> Church and Kingdom, that the antient Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical <hi>cenſures,</hi> pennances, injunctions, <hi>ſuſpenſions,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>privations and excommunications were reſtored to their <hi>primitive</hi> uſe, that offenders of all <hi>ſiſes</hi> may be puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but Clergy men eſpecially with <hi>rigour,</hi> that the <hi>name</hi> of God may not be blaſphemed any longer through <hi>them,</hi> ſince now we have an <hi>authority</hi> which no man can except againſt: I know it will be ſaid that many a man hath been <hi>caſt out</hi> for ſcandal, that was was unblam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able: So indeed was the <hi>unjuſt proceſs</hi> of the Tryers; it cannot but be confeſſed; whoſe cauſe ought to be <hi>heard</hi> over again, and in conſcience he ſhould be <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored,</hi> but ſhall even ſuch notorious offenders over whom <hi>Conſtantine</hi> ſaid, <hi>Paludamento ſe obtecturum,</hi> he would caſt over his cloak to hide their <hi>ſhame,</hi> be plead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for, when the voice of <hi>Town</hi> and Countrey ſhall
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:168928:10"/>tell you that they are common drunkards, <hi>fornicators,</hi> ſwearers, and pittifully inſufficient for the work of the <hi>Miniſtry,</hi> if you will but bring them to a tryal; It is moſt true, they had not <hi>competent</hi> Judges; no more had any other <hi>malefactors,</hi> and evil doers which were deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vedly <hi>condemned</hi> for their crimes proved by witneſſes upon their <hi>oaths</hi> againſt them, or elſe what <hi>living</hi> had there been for men under a <hi>tyrannicall</hi> power? is not here the ſame caſe? There wanted the <hi>outward form</hi> of a Judge, but the matter is evidently <hi>proved</hi> againſt them, that it was <hi>intolerable</hi> ſuch men ſhould be continued; if competent Judges muſt invalidate all proceedings for this <hi>twelve</hi> years, I wonder why all the ſuites and tryals of Law ſhould be confirmed that have been? I know many alſo are of this judgement, that theſe ſhould be <hi>admoniſhed</hi> before put out of their livings, and if they be <hi>admoniſhed</hi> now before the <hi>Biſhop,</hi> for their ſcandall, it is <hi>ſufficient.</hi> I muſt needs anſwer, that <hi>ſome crimes</hi> of Miniſters fall rightly under admonition, <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proof,</hi> and Eccleſiaſtical <hi>cenſure</hi> to puniſh the offence; but others are of that <hi>Nature</hi> as deſerve immediate <hi>expulſion</hi> from the Church, for holding ſo ſacred an Office, as in the Miniſtry, according to that <hi>canon</hi> of the Apoſtles, <hi>Clericus in fornicatione deprehenſus depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natur.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Apoſt. can. <hi>25.</hi>
               </note> A Clergy man taken in fornication, let him be put aſide his office: have not ſome been proved guilty of this crime? and ſhall they be reſtored to the Church? in light offences we muſt admoniſh, but in great puniſh greatly; and have we not for this the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> when <hi>Williams</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Lincoln</hi> was deprived <hi>ab officio &amp; beneficio,</hi> and fined a good ſum of <hi>money</hi> beſides; was he <hi>admoniſhed</hi> before he was put out of all? no; becauſe his crime was of that ſcandalous <hi>nature,</hi> that the <hi>Archbiſhop</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led him a <hi>Son of Belial,</hi> he had no ſuch act of favour as admonition. <hi>Eli</hi> thought that might expiate his <hi>Sons</hi> wickedneſs when he reproved them for misbeha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving <hi>themſelves</hi> ſo ſcandalouſly in the Prieſts <hi>office,</hi> but
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:168928:11"/>God accepted not of this <hi>purgation</hi> of their ſin, but brought a judgement upon the old mans houſe for ever, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.32. So the inceſtuous man by St. <hi>Pauls</hi> letter of excommunication, was put away immediately, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.13. The rule is excellent in this caſe, <hi>Si quidem mediocre eſt peccatum, monere, &amp; ſuſpendere, &amp; paenitentia ei dare tempus, ut in meliorem ordinem ſacrum mox revertatur ad ſemetipſum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Juſtin. Tit. <hi>17.</hi> N. <hi>134.</hi>
               </note> if it be a mean offence, then to <hi>admoniſh</hi> and ſuſpend him for it, and give him time for <hi>repentance,</hi> untill following a better <hi>courſe</hi> he returns to <hi>himſelf</hi> again. What are mean offences? ſhall we ſay common drinking, ſwearing, <hi>whoring,</hi> or ſuch like? God <hi>forbid;</hi> he that makes no conſcience to defile his ſoul with theſe ſins, <hi>Peccata conſcientiam vaſtantia,</hi> which lay waſte the <hi>conſcience,</hi> it is not fit he ſhould have the <hi>government</hi> of other mens ſouls and <hi>conſciences</hi> committed to him; and though he may ſhew ſome outward <hi>ſigns</hi> of repentance and reformation af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward (for which let him receive due encouragement by his attendance on ſome <hi>inferiour office,</hi> as the Prieſts did of old, and have ſome <hi>competent</hi> maintenance for his labour,) yet it is not fit he ſhould be intruſted with the ſame <hi>charge</hi> he had before, no more then he who hath <hi>falſly</hi> and corruptly <hi>behaved</hi> himſelf in a place of the Common-wealth, ſhould be <hi>continued</hi> in it, nor upon his outward <hi>ſhew</hi> of more honeſt <hi>carriage</hi> to mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter in any other then an <hi>inferiour</hi> office.</p>
            <p>Then let us conſider <hi>ſeriouſly,</hi> who fear and tremble at the <hi>judgement</hi> of God, who hath afflicted us many <hi>years,</hi> for our ſin, firſt beginning at his <hi>own</hi> houſe, then going to the <hi>houſe</hi> of our <hi>King,</hi> and viſiting all our <hi>fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies</hi> with plagues, as he did <hi>Aegypt;</hi> if we harden our hearts againſt the <hi>ſenſe</hi> of his former <hi>judgements,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we live under the <hi>fruition</hi> of preſent mercies; if we know not how to improve theſe <hi>ſtupendious provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences,</hi> that he hath <hi>wrought</hi> with his own arm, and by the hand alſo of our <hi>profeſſed</hi> enemies, who have long <hi>trodden</hi> upon our necks, but now they bow their <hi>ſheaf</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:168928:11"/>to us; we muſt expect, if we return to <hi>our old</hi> profaneſs, riots, wantonneſs and <hi>liberty</hi> in our carriage, that ſin will drive our <hi>Jordan</hi> back from us, in all its <hi>pleaſant ſtreams;</hi> if we ſoar too high with waxen wings, we ſhall melt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Sun; our only care is to be <hi>examples</hi> of great ſtrictneſs, <hi>watchfulneſs,</hi> and circumſpection of our <hi>lives,</hi> &amp; labour that above all <hi>orders</hi> of men, the Clergy, which is the peculiar tribe <hi>beloved</hi> of God, be in nothing <hi>blamed,</hi> but that ſuch who are a ſcandall to their <hi>calling</hi> be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed according to the <hi>diſcipline</hi> of former times, and that we follow thoſe <hi>rules</hi> of ſtrictneſs which the holy Scripture, the <hi>laws</hi> of our Church, and the Canons of <hi>Antient</hi> times hath enjoyned; St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſets forth the qualities of being blameleſs, which might be a ſufficient word comprehending all;<note place="margin">1 Tim. 3.2.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> doth not ſignifie faultleſs; for there are no ſuch in the <hi>world,</hi> but a man that is not tainted with any common <hi>blemiſh</hi> of ſcandal; ſo he is not to be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is, given to wine, not only to be free from <hi>drunkenneſs,</hi> but from fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent drinking; <hi>vino aſſidens ad perpotandum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Calv. in loc.</note> ſaith <hi>Guhard,</hi> a Tavern <hi>Stake,</hi> ſitting <hi>cloſe</hi> to his cups; <hi>tipling</hi> is forbidden; <hi>non ebrietatem ſed quamvis intemperiem in vino ingurgitando,</hi> ſaith <hi>Calvin,</hi> not only drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs but intemperate <hi>guttling</hi> of wine; the Apoſtle know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what follows the <hi>diſorder</hi> of immoderate drinking, commands in the next <hi>place,</hi> that he ſhould be no ſtriker; <hi>cognata vitia ſunt vinolentia &amp; violentia,</hi> as one ſaith, theſe two are coſen <hi>germans,</hi> drinking and fighting: when wine fumes into the <hi>head,</hi> the quarrell begins: above all other, theſe are moſt <hi>unbeſeeming</hi> the profeſſion of a Miniſter; yet the Church of <hi>England</hi> takes notice of other <hi>crimes</hi> that are adjudged ſcandalous by her; The book of <hi>reformation</hi> of Eccleſiaſticall Laws, that was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun to be <hi>compiled</hi> in <hi>Henry</hi> the eighths reign, and after carried on to a perfection in <hi>Edward</hi> 6. by whom it was confirmed with the approbation of ſuch <hi>Biſhops</hi> as were godly <hi>Martyrs</hi> of the Church after, we find <hi>writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten</hi> therein concerning our <hi>Clergy, Non ſint compoto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:168928:12"/>non Aleatores, non aucupes, non venatores, non Syco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phantae, non otioſi, aut ſupini, ſed ſacrarum literarum ſtudiis, praedicationi &amp; orationi incumbant:</hi> They muſt not be good <hi>fellows, dicers,</hi> hawkers, <hi>hunters</hi> nor Syco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phants, idle neligent <hi>perſons,</hi> but apply themſelves to the <hi>ſtudy</hi> of holy Scrptures, and to meditation and prayer; ſo we may ſee how <hi>ſtrict</hi> our firſt <hi>reformers</hi> from Popery were; ſo far from indulging groſs ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dals, as not to ſuffer the <hi>lawfull recreations</hi> of hunting and hawking among Clergy men, who ſhould be exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples to refrain from ſuch <hi>idle pleaſures</hi> as others might enjoy. And to ſhew how agreeable was the conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our Church to the <hi>ſtrictneſs</hi> of primitive times, unto which it was <hi>excellently</hi> framed by the <hi>Prelates</hi> thereof, we find thoſe times enforcing <hi>great ſeverity</hi> of behaviour in the Clergy above all other, which was the occaſion I ſuppoſe of thoſe <hi>ſtrict</hi> laws of our Church, <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 364.<note place="margin">Laodic: concil. can. <hi>54.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Non licere clericis ludicris ſpectaculis intereſſe.</hi> It is not lawull for <hi>Clergy</hi> men to be preſent at <hi>ſtages-playes; Non Chriſtanorum comeſſalibus intereſſe,</hi> nor preſent at common <hi>feaſts</hi> of Chriſtians.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Can.</hi> 53.</note> 
               <hi>In Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianorum non ſaltetur nuptiis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Can.</hi> 5.</note> he muſt not <hi>dance</hi> at weddings.<note place="margin">Nic. concil. can. <hi>18.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Clericus uſurarius deponatur,</hi> An uſurer who is a Clergy man muſt be <hi>depoſed</hi> from his office. <hi>Quadrageſimam non jejunans deponatur,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lib. Conc. can. <hi>20.</hi>
               </note> this is to be underſtood <hi>in caſe</hi> he had his <hi>health,</hi> or otherwiſe he might <hi>break Lent.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Conc. Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>och. can. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> Being convicted of ſcandal, no <hi>ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal</hi> ſhould be made to the <hi>Emperour</hi> by the <hi>Council of Antioch.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Since that we are now <hi>rebuilding</hi> our ſpiritual <hi>temple</hi> after ſo long a <hi>captivity</hi> of twenty years that it hath been <hi>laid waſte</hi> by Gods judgement on us, and made an <hi>abomination</hi> of deſolation for our profaneſs, liberty, <hi>ſcandal,</hi> tranſgreſſion both of humane and <hi>divine laws,</hi> which very ſins were the occaſion of the deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the <hi>Jews</hi> Temple and City, as <hi>Joſephus</hi> tells us, let us with all our <hi>diligence,</hi> now the ſtones are to be ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered up, not build our new <hi>City</hi> and Temple with any
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:168928:12"/>other <hi>materials</hi> then are precious <hi>ſtones,</hi> that is, <hi>juſt,</hi> holy, <hi>righteous,</hi> and truly <hi>religious</hi> men of ſanctified lives, that we may have the ſame <hi>divine policy</hi> of Presbyteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, only differing in the better <hi>end</hi> propoſed, that <hi>what they do out of faction and gaining a greater party to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, as</hi> Dr. Taylor <hi>ſaith we may out of conſcience</hi> ſhew that Epiſcopal men are of ſtrict ſevere courſe of life, and as zealous to <hi>keep</hi> off ſcandal from our <hi>Church</hi> and ſacred <hi>Ordinances</hi> as they are; and never let us think that God will <hi>bleſs</hi> our Church, to continue it in <hi>peace,</hi> unity and <hi>glory,</hi> unleſs we vigorouſly put in execution its former <hi>laws of diſcipline,</hi> and the Clergy be <hi>exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plary</hi> in piety <hi>above all</hi> others, that they live like the <hi>primitive</hi> Chriſtians, whoſe lives excelled the <hi>ſtricteſt laws</hi> of the Empire. So theirs muſt excell <hi>the laws</hi> of their order, and in the mean time keep out <hi>ſcandalous</hi> men from blemiſhing their ſociety; if otherwiſe we build our <hi>Temple,</hi> the building will be but in <hi>vain,</hi> when we think to <hi>re-edifie it</hi> by the miniſtery of the ſame <hi>hands</hi> which have pulled it down.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
